A Finding Aid to the Agnes Mills Papers, 1948-1999, bulk 1974-1993, in the Archives of American Art AAA.millagne
Archives of American Art
Agnes Mills papers
bulk 1974-1993
1948-1999
AAA.millagne
Archives of American Art
1.1 Linear feet
The papers of painter, printmaker and sculptor Agnes Mills measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1948 to 1999, with the bulk of the material from 1974 to 1993. Her enduring interest in dance theatre is demonstrated in the papers. Reminiscences of her time in the WPA, artist statements, sketchbooks, and a bound compilation of publicity, biographical notes, and images of artwork provide an overview of her professional accomplishments. The collection also includes curricula vitae; correspondence; writings by and about the artist; price lists and inventories; articles, news clippings, press releases and exhibition announcements; original artwork; and photographs of both the artist and her work.
Mills, Agnes, 1915-2008
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1982-1990 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1974-1999 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1980s-1990 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1981-1993 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1948-1993 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 1, OV2; 0.2 linear feef)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, circa 1974-circa 1993 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1948-1993 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Agnes Mills (1915-2008) was a painter, printmaker and sculptor who specialized in dance subjects. She worked in the Long Island/New York City area for most of her career, eventually moving to Florida.
Mills was a graduate of Pratt Institute and Cooper Union Art School and worked for the WPA artist project early in her career. For 25 years she served as resident artist for the Alwin Nikolais Dance Company, and several other dance companies hired her to sketch their rehearsals.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, printmaker and sculptor Agnes Mills measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1948 to 1999, with the bulk of the material from 1974 to 1993. Her enduring interest in dance theatre is demonstrated in the papers. Reminiscences of her time in the WPA, artist statements, sketchbooks, and a bound compilation of publicity, biographical notes, and images of artwork provide an overview of her professional accomplishments. The collection also includes curricula vitae; correspondence; writings by and about Mills; price lists and inventories; articles, news clippings, press releases and exhibition announcements; original artwork; and photographs of Mills and her work.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by the artist's daughter, Margret Mills-Thysen, on October 17, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment.
United States. Works Progress Administration.; Dance; Painters--Florida; Painters--New York (State); Printmakers--Florida; Printmakers--New York (State); Prints; Sculptors--Florida; Sculptors--New York (State); Sketchbooks; Women artists--Florida; Women artists--New York
- Biographical Material, 1982-1990; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes curricula vitae and biographical notes.
  - Biographical Materials, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1974-1999; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is with galleries, publications, Nikolais Dance Theatre, and Murray Louis Dance Company.
  - Correspondence, 1974-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings, circa 1980s-1990; Series 3; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include artist's statements and reminiscences of the WPA artist project. Writings about the artist consist of remarks delivered by Norma Reiner at an exhibition opening.
  - Writings by Agnes Mills, circa 1980s-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings about Agnes Mills, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Personal Business Records, 1981-1993; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Various inventories, price lists, and receipts are included in this series.
  - Personal Business Records, 1981-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Printed Material, 1948-1993; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  All printed material mentions Agnes Mills or features reproductions of her work.
  - Press Releases and Exhibition Announcements, 1948-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1948-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Bound Copies of Publicity and Artwork, 1948-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Artwork, circa 1950s-1990s; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV2
  This series includes sketches in ink, marker, paste and crayon, as well as some monoprints.
  - Artwork, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Oversized material housed in OV2.
  - Oversized Artwork (from Box 1 Folder 12), circa 1950s-1990s (Box OV2)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1974-circa 1993; Series 7; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Six sketchbooks (3 are accordion style) include landscapes, dancers, and abstract work in gouache ink, pastel, and pencil.
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1974-circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
- Photographs, circa 1948-1993; Series 8; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographs are in color and black and white. There are formal portraits of the artist as well as candid views. Works by Mills include paintings, drawings and sculpture. There are 2 loose pages from a photograph album and several negatives.
  - Photographs of Agnes Mills, circa 1948-circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1974-circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16-18)